<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Think out loud</title><link href="http://kotfic.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://kotfic.github.io/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://kotfic.github.io/</id><updated>2015-04-08T00:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Hierarchies, Tagging and Personal Information Management</title><link href="http://kotfic.github.io/hierarchies-tagging-and-personal-information-management.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-04-08T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Christopher Kotfila</name></author><id>tag:kotfic.github.io,2015-04-08:hierarchies-tagging-and-personal-information-management.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Org-mode has a dizzying array of features for organizing an infinite number of work flows.  For a long time I resisted learning org-mode because it seemed too complex. Anecdotally the problem most people seem to have when starting with org-mode is org supports so many different ways of organizing information without any expectations or guidance on how to apply org's tools to your own personal information landscape. Org-mode is built around hierarchical outlines and so it supports organizing information in tree structures quite well. Tree structures can be quite limiting- especially when there are leaf nodes that you 'feel' should belong in multiple branches of a tree.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been trying to think about this feeling, and I think what it boils down to is providing &lt;em&gt;access&lt;/em&gt; to the information we record.  We write things down because at some point the number of things we need to manage overwhelms our cognitive system. We lack the ability to keep track of everything in our mind.  By writing them down the cognitive task shifts towards keeping track of where we have put the information rather than keeping track of the information itself. We maintain complex mental models of pointers to the information we need. What happens when our pointer based models (reading lists, TODO lists, calendars, etc)  overwhelm our cognitive system?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the question that catalogers have been trying to answer since &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Library_of_Alexandria"&gt;Alexandria&lt;/a&gt;. Catalogers are primarily concerned about formal models of &lt;a href="http://www.abc-clio.com/ODLIS/odlis_a.aspx#accesspoint"&gt;access&lt;/a&gt; to information. To this end in 1998 the International Federation of Library Associations and Institutions (IFLA) came out with recommendations called the &lt;a href="http://www.ifla.org/publications/functional-requirements-for-bibliographic-records"&gt;Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records&lt;/a&gt; (FRBR).  FRBR is essentially an &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Entity%25E2%2580%2593relationship_model"&gt;entity-relationship&lt;/a&gt; model for managing works,  expressions, manifestations and items (e.g., books, periodicals, dvd's etc),  it is intended to replace a 'flat' record-based information model that is currently in use. FRBR is a huge specification and obviously makes no sense in the context of my personal notes and research. However the idea of functional requirements for my own information management is appealing.  In the next couple of blog posts I'm interested in trying to develop my own informal functional requirements for (my) personal information management (FRPIM?). I'll start with an outline:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Facts about Org-Mode&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Org-mode supports hierarchies&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hierarchies can be &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holonymy"&gt;holonym&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meronymy"&gt;meronym&lt;/a&gt; (has-a) relationships&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hierarchies can be &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyponymy_and_hypernymy"&gt;hypernyms/hyponymns&lt;/a&gt; (is-a) relationships&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Org-mode supports tagging&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tagging are more flexible, tags can represent anything&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tagging needs tighter controls to ensure it provides effective access&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tag authority (e.g., &lt;a href="http://www.loc.gov/marc/uma/pt1-7.html#pt4"&gt;authority records&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;thematic tag groups (projects, subjects, action types (e.g., read, write, email) ?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Org-mode supports networks (sort of)&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;linking between headlines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the difference between a network and a bunch of linked files?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What do I do now?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;empirical evidence?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why is this working&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why is it not working?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What should I do?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What aspects of my personal information should the org-mode hierarchy model?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What tag themes should exist?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can I control the tag fixed vocabulary?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;How to transition?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have ~50,000 lines of notes, how do I transition these into the new system?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What about process based PIM?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems like really good information systems should be predictive. They should provide the information that you need '&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Just-in-time_compilation"&gt;Just-in-time&lt;/a&gt;.' The most obvious reason this might not be a good idea is &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Office_Assistant"&gt;Clippy&lt;/a&gt;. Is predictive information management just a bad idea? Or is it an issue of control over how predictive information management interfaces with a work flow? If you implemented a system like this how would you empirically know it was working?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="org-mode"></category><category term="emacs"></category></entry><entry><title>Goals for Managing Pelican from Org-Mode</title><link href="http://kotfic.github.io/managing-pelican-from-org-mode.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-04-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Christopher Kotfila</name></author><id>tag:kotfic.github.io,2015-04-04:managing-pelican-from-org-mode.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;It Begins&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've recently decided that I would like to start blogging. This is for a couple of reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Giving Back&lt;/strong&gt; I have benefited immensely from blogs and websites where individuals who have suffered through difficult technical travails have shared the minutia of their suffering and saved me countless hours similar suffering.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Self reflection&lt;/strong&gt; I have noticed a lack of self reflection in my day to day work. I hope a more disciplined approach to writing will help me to be more thoughtful about the work choices I make. I often feel overwhelmed by the processes I implement to manage the various papers,  classes, projects, research and software I work on.  I am hoping that by writing out clear goals for these various elements I will be able to better assess my progress and pivot when things aren't working.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Because I should&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="http://sachachua.com/blog/"&gt;Sacha Chua&lt;/a&gt; is the last in a long line of individuals that I respect who have recommended writing daily to improve my communication skills. As a burgeoning researcher I am (begrudgingly) starting to accept that I will need more skills than just software development to be successful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;It gets technical&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I manage most of my life in &lt;a href="http://orgmode.org/"&gt;Org Mode&lt;/a&gt; which is a mode of the text editor &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/"&gt;Emacs&lt;/a&gt;. Org Mode (with contributions) is a whopping 136,000+ lines of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emacs_Lisp"&gt;Emacs Lisp&lt;/a&gt;. It is really an application all in its own,  I use it to organize my classes, my research, my software and personal life. I'm pleased to say I am also using it to write this blog. Along with &lt;a href="https://danlamanna.com/"&gt;a friend&lt;/a&gt; I am working on developing a small Org Mode export library for the &lt;a href="http://blog.getpelican.com/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; static website generator. The code is available &lt;a href="https://github.com/kotfic/ox-pelican"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. At the time of writing this blog there is just a small minimum viable product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Why roll my own?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a bunch of great libraries out there already not the least of which is the &lt;a href="http://orgmode.org/manual/Publishing.html"&gt;Org Publish&lt;/a&gt; workflow for exporting from your org files to your hierarchical text format of choice. Unfortunately none of these met my goals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manage all posts and pages from a single Org Mode file. &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This might end up being a bottle neck if I end up with thousands of posts (burn that bridge when we get there)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Separate concerns&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Org Mode is for managing content,  Pelican is for publishing to the web.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relatively light weight,&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do common tasks well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Edge cases should be handled by hand&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pelican should be completely unaware that Org Mode and Emacs are involved.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manage pelican post meta-data from the Org Mode property drawer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integrate into the org export workflow as much as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Possible problems&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few areas where this might fall flat on its face:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Org Mode can export files to pelican's content directory but it can't clean up without keeping track of what it has exported.  There are ways around this but it could get heavy very quickly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If there are lots of posts (over 1000?) in a single file we may have performance issues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><category term="emacs"></category><category term="org-mode"></category><category term="pelican"></category></entry></feed>